Hello my name is Gina Bai, I am a assistant professor of the practice at Vanderbilt and
I am excited to be here to talk about how novice testers perceive and perform testing.
We will be focusing on unit testing which is the most basic level of software testing.
So to begin with I would like you to make a guess - you can share that on Slack - so how much does
poor software quality cost the U.S in 2022? [pause]
Make a great - brave guess.
$1.4 billion? It's actually at least $2.41 trillion.
That's about 10% of the GDP if you asked of that year.
I know this is horrible, right, and I'm sure this will raise the awareness of
testing as a critical engineering activity, as well as the awareness that our developers
and of course our testers need to be able to perform testing well.
However, Titus Winters, who's a principal software engineer at Google,
pointed out that most of their new grad hires unfortunately have
very limited experience with testing. So testing skills and knowledge is one
of the gaps between CS education programs and industry expectations of graduating students.
It is an open question for all of us how to establish - how to enhance students,
the new hires, or let's say the novices' testing skills.
So to do so the first step is to learn how novices perceive and perform testing.
For most novices they see no difference between testing and debugging or think that the purpose of
testing is to show the correctness of the program. Because in most CS education programs - especially
the undergraduate programs - students are usually expected
to implement their programs given the description: make sure they compile, they run, they pass all
the test cases provided by the instructors. And in some courses students are also expected
to write their own tests - to test their own programs or programs implemented by their peers.
But in general if all test cases pass that usually means that's awesome the
program is ready for submission. If not it's time to debug.
So I would say it's not surprising at all to see that novices feel like - they have a blurred
conceptual line between testing and debugging. But the question is can we say a program
is 100% correct or is it perfect if they pass all the test cases?
Could it be the case that the testing is just not effective enough to
capture - to review the failure, or could it be the case that some
of the tests themselves are just not correctly designed and implemented?
So what we are trying to do is to train the novices - to help them build the tester's mindset,
and to be able to identify - to figure out the testing scenarios,
especially the corner cases that may break the program.
So that's the level two thinking. And of course we want to help the
novices to eventually get to level three - to realize that testing can only show the presence
of the failures but not their absence. We test the programs - we test the
software to reduce their risk of causing bad consequences or even catastrophes.
And let testers' mindset actually guide us to better design and develop the software.
So that's how novices perceive testing, and let's see how they practice unit testing.
We conducted several studies exploring their testing behaviors and performance
and here I'll present several representative questions from the novices.
So the first one: Amy had a typical question when the novices are going
up to level two from level one. She was not sure how to interpret
and handle a test that failed. Is it okay to have a failing test?
Does it mean a bug in the source code? Or is it a mistake in the test code?
We observe several cases in which the participants - the novices - even though,
even when they were informed that there were at least one bug in the code
they still trust the code over the program specifications
and they try to cover that source code regardless of the correctness.
And Bob needed guidance on when to stop testing. Is it determined by the number of test cases,
could it be - should it be the case that everything needs to be tested,
and how to make sure everything is tested?
Can we stop testing after, for example, finding one bug?
This can actually be like - this question can actually be partially solved by
consulting coverage tools like EclEmma which tells you - the user whether the
test cases are actually covering the source code and how much the code is exercise.
But we observed no adoption of tools like these in our studies.
This also suggests the lack of exposure to testing tools for novices.
At the same time we also observe some extreme cases in which the novices wrote
dozens of tests for just one single method and all of them were testing the happy path.
Charlie had difficulty in reusing the code examples from online resources
and Daniel cannot figure out how to actually implement a test to
indicate the existence of the bug. So in our study we also found several
novices where - who were able to identify to design the unhappy path test cases
but they ended up deleting all the test cases only because they cannot figure out
the correct syntax, For example to assert
an exception is thrown so they just gave up. But in general novices found it challenging
to determine what to test and how to test. They have no consensus on what makes a unit
good and hence novices find it challenging to determine when to stop testing
and they tend to only - to only test the happy path.
Additionally novices often create test cases that mismatch the program specifications
and they face implementation barriers. This could be from their - the lack of
hands-on testing practices or it could be some misunderstanding of the program descriptions.
But in response to those challenges and with the consideration of cognitive load,
well, for novices they have to
learn using tags, new concepts, new libraries, new tools to be able to practice testing
so we hope to keep the extra cognitive load as minimal as possible when we
introduce them to our support. So we introduce a lightweight
checklist intervention. Why checklists?
Since checklists were able to - they're so simple, right, and they're also super useful
in other software engineering research areas such as code review and software inspection
and a big feature of the checklist is that it is static
which reduces the learning curve for novice testers
and it is lightweight enough to be transferred across classrooms,
training programs, and languages, including natural languages and programming languages.
And if we take a closer look at the checklist items,
we can see that it is separated into two levels of abstractions,
one for test cases and one for test suites.
Each abstraction level also has two sets of checklist items,
the items that they should do, representing the important required
elements and items that they could do representing the best testing practices.
So it contains tutorial information, it briefly introduces the use
of test class components. The checklist also provides
the testing strategies - for example equivalence class partitioning and boundary value testing.
We didn't explicitly name those strategies in the checklist because they're novices,
so instead we reminded them to think about those cases.
What's more the checklist items are also designed to address the common mistakes and test smells
that are observed in prior studies as well as the in the classrooms
and you can see bad naming is one of them, just like what Christian said, the naming matters.
And the checklist is definitely not a like golden standard for practicing testing
but it helps the novices to write tests that are of good quality and reduce the number
of - on one day unneeded redundant tests. And we found out the checklist works well
and it is at least as effective as a coverage tool like EclEmma for writing quality tests for novices
which indicates that the tool support does not need to be
sophisticated to be mature, to be effective. And we also found that the novices who have
lower prior knowledge in unit testing should benefit more from the checklist.
To summarize, most novice testers see no difference between testing and debugging,
they cannot build them, and they believe the goal
of testing is to show the correctness. We discussed the challenges that they
encountered when practicing testing and we also showed that tool support
does not need to be sophisticated to begin with - a simple checklist will sometimes do the magic.
And I'll open to the questions.
Yeah fantastic, thank you so much Gina, again another great talk, we have time for questions
though if folks do have any please feel free to be putting those in the Slack.
I'll kind of kick things off. I really find this really interesting especially
since since I've been working at George Mason and I've been teaching a software testing class
and reflecting on my own CS education I realized that I never had that type of education
in my - you know, explicitly and in depth, right,
with what it means to write tests, to think about tests.
Do you think that part of the problem that led to this research is that we're not
focusing on that enough at a deeper level and do you think that interventions like
this could also support how we teach testing for example?
Well, because that's my work so I am probably biased,
but the reason why I started to work on testing education is that I personally
didn't receive any testing education, like, formal testing education,
when I was an undergrad I didn't see testing until in grad school doing my PhD work.
So I feel it is important for us to at least try something that's not that hard to adopt for both
students and professors to apply, to help them to teach testing,
help them to learn testing. And this is just again because not many professors
had a formal education or background in testing so they probably
won't touch that deep level of testing, so again most in most cases the practice is to
just have the students run it - run their program against their
test cases provided by the instructors and sometimes the test cases performed - provided
by the instructors are not even good enough. So absolutely,
I feel like the testing - the checklist may work as a good,
at least a minimal threshold of what your tests need to cover.